Guide to the records of the Musical Acoustics Research Library (MARL) M1711
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 1. Catgut Acoustical Society Collection, 1963-2007; 24.186 Linear Feet
  - Condax, Louis M. - Correspondence with Dr. Guillermo A. Fraser, violin bridge expert, 1967; C7450-502 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Publications by Louis Couturier and C. E. Mertzanoff, 1942-; C7450-503 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    Louis Couturier. 40 Jaar Max Möllers Vioolbouw 1913-1953; C. E. Mertzanoff. The Perfection of the Strad Design.
  - Condax, Louis M. - Fossil Wood, 1970; C7450-504 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Condax, Louis M. - I.R. Spectra. Techler, Rosen, Shellac, 1970; C7450-505 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Labels of Old Luthier Masters, C7450-506 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Various materials on violin coloring and varnish, C7450-507 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    2 sets of violin images: rapid half tone: two Strads from 35 mm, Sacconi; Natural Dc/es-coloring matter; Rosen patent; article on rubber chemistry
  - Condax, Louis M. - Photos and letter on the Ratnagar Strad, 1964; C7450-508 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    Letter from F.R. Ratnagar to Condax; Publication by Ratnagar on Antonio Stradivari
  - Condax, Louis M. - Dave Rubinoff, 1966-1970; C7450-509 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    Correspondence to and by Rubinoff; photographs, autographed program
  - Condax, Louis M. - Tertis Viola, 1943-1950; C7450-601 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    Talk: Lionel Tertis. The Tertis Model Viola; Program; Diagrams of the improved Tertis model 16 3/4 inch viola, revised in 1949 and 1953
  - Condax, Louis M. - Violin Acoustics, 1940-1967; C7450-602 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    16 published articles
  - Condax, Louis M. - On the Violin's Sound Post, 1963-1964; C7450-603 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    Unpublished papers and photographs
  - Condax, Louis M. - Domenico Dragonetti's Gasparo da Salo String Bass, 1910; C7450-604 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    Publication, 15 pages
  - Condax, Louis M. - Photos: viols, C7450-605 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    10 photos: bass viols, viola d'amore, and vila da gamba
  - Condax, Louis M. - Article: Physics and Music, 1948; C7450-606 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Photos and Publication, C7450-607 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    Letter from Franz F. Lyon; Article: Victor A. McKusick and H. Kenneth Wisking. Felix Savart (1791-1841), Physician-Physicist. Early Studies Pertinent to the Understanding of Murmurs; Negatives and photos: Goerz Strad and Hermann Book
  - Condax, Louis M. - Spectrum Analysis of Violin Varnish, C7450-608 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Condax, Louis M. - On Violin Construction and Bows, 1903-1965; C7450-609 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    Article: Condax. A Plea and a Suggestion for a Guide, Standard, Principle or Measuring Device to Compare and Evaluate Completed Musical Bows; Tolbecque measurements 1903; Viola outline by Hutchins
  - Condax, Louis M. - Violin models. Half-tone prints, Le Duc Guarneri, 1946-; C7450-610 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Publications: World of Strings, 1962-1968; C7450-611 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Notebooks on violin varnish experiments, 1937-1959; C7450-701 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Notebooks on violin varnish experiments, 1944-1950; C7450-702 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Notebooks on violin varnish experiments, 1951-1957; C7450-703 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Notebooks on violin varnish experiments, 1958-1966; C7450-704 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Notebooks on violin varnish experiments, 1967-1970; C7450-705 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Notebooks on violin varnish experiments, 1969-1970; C7450-706 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Notebooks on violin varnish experiments, C7450-707 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Condax, Louis M. - Varnish samples on wood, 1987; C7450-801 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Corliss, Edith L.R. - Correspondence and Technical Papers, 1964-1995; C8052-101 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    Correspondence with Carleen Hutchins; Various papers on the hearing and the ear as a mechanism of communication
    Corliss, Edith L. R.
  - Creel Warren - Correspondence, 1968-1989; C9135-101 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    Correspondence: between Creel & wife Marie and CMH. Others are REF, V Apgar, A H. Benade, Betty Goodfriend, JCS, regarding Nomination for Fellows of ASA. Also, CMH to various contributors to CAS in his memory.
    Warren Creel and Paul Boomsliter worked together closely in the field of auditory perception and organization, studying pitch relations and durational effects in tonal perception, sensation, rhythm and cadence in language which they studied through music and poetry with related psychoacoustic studies, including animal experimentation. Starting in the early 1960s, Warren worked as a research associate in the Department of Surgery, Albany Medical College, after an early career in teaching. His interest in the work of the CAS started in the mid 1960s, both in the research and development as well as in the functioning of the Society, which lasted until his death. He was chairman of the Committee on By-Laws, for many years Treasurer, and later Vice-President. His own research in psychoacoustics complimented much that we were doing on the development of the new instruments of the Violin Octet. Warren was great fun to work with and always had some interesting new ideas, and arguments could go on far into the night. This file contains mostly correspondence. For his published papers and research work see the file of Paul Boomsliter.
    Creel, Warren
  - Creel Warren - Miscellaneous, 1968-1976; C9135-102 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    Miscellaneous: Bibliography; Albany Med Center Bulletin article; Book Review of `Sounds of Music' by C Taylor and supplemental article on `Musical Intonation for Fiddlers'; Poem: `The Cellulose-Graphite Process for Helium Carbide' - Musings on the performance score in an intelligence test.
  - Creel Warren - Technical Papers, 1967-1975; C9135-103 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    Technical: 5 papers (1967-1975). Creel and others - one by Massaro alone discussing work of Creel, Boomsliter & Powers. Topics: Preprocessed brain signals; tonal sensation; auditory perception; processing time for auditory signals.
  - Cremer, Lothar - Correspondence, 1970-1990; C9160-101 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    CMH first met Professor Cremer, one of the most important acousticians of this century in Germany, when he lectured at MIT. He was pleased to find violin acoustics being studied in the US and subsequently invited her to lecture at the Heinrich Hertz Institute in Berlin, of which he was Director. She was finally able to accept this invitation in 1971 in conjunction with her trip to the ICA Meeting in Budapest. Over the years there developed a close friendship and an active correspondence sharing technical information ensued. CMH was instrumental in his receiving the ASA Gold Medal. The high regard in which he was held will be evident from the biographical detail found in the Miscellaneous section (102) of this file, and the significance of his contribution to acoustics may be assessed from the number of awards he received and from the extent of the obituary material to be found there. His published output is vast - over 100 papers and several books. A few of the many are contained in sections 103 & 104. See the Technical Summary.
    Correspondence: between Creel & wife Marie and CMH. Others are REF, V Apgar, A H Benade, Betty Goodfriend, JCS, regarding Nomination for Fellows of ASA. Also, CMH to various contributors to CAS in his memory.
    Cremer, Lothar
  - Cremer, Lothar - Miscellaneous, 1974-1990; C9160-102 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Cremer, Lothar - Technical Papers, 1968-1990; C9160-103 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    Technical: 5 papers Creel and others - one by Massaro alone discussing work of Creel, Boomsliter & Powers. See Tech Summary. Topics: Preprocessed brain signals | tonal sensation | auditory perception | processing time for auditory signals.
  - Cremer, Lothar - Technical Book, 1988; 9160-104 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    Physik der Geige; Review by G. Weinreich and review of English translation: The Physics of the Violin. Topics: bowing; violin body vibrations; sound radiation.
  - Dickens, Fred T. - Correspondence and Technical Papers on the Guitar, 1975-1997; D5485-101 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    Dickens, Fred T
  - Duhamel, Jean Marie Constant - Technical Paper, 1841; D8690-101 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    Tech paper (1) in French and translation of his 1841 memoire on the action of the bow on the string abstract. Miscellaneous: Entry from Dictionary of Scientific Biography 1971. Topics: Bowed string | Stick/slip action
    A mathematician known to students of calculus and of heat who published a paper on the bowed string in which he recognized the need to consider two parts of a period of vibration, sticking and slipping. He derided the idea that the vibrations of the bowed string are caused by the plucking action of barbs on the bow hair -- a concept that still plagues us. He failed to understand a fact later recognized by Helmholtz that wave propagation along the string is not instantaneous, but occurs with finite velocity, thus freeing the string from the bow not as a result of increase in stress between the two, but because the sharp kink in the string has suddenly returned after reflection from the nut.
    Duhamel, M. (Jean Marie Constant)
  - Eggers, Frieder - Correspondence with Carleen M. Hutchins, 1964-1992; E2960-101 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    Research physicist and cellist who did the first thorough study of vibration modes (1959) in which not only nodal lines, but also contours of amplitude were plotted giving amplitude and phase. He also measured the mechanical impedance at several points. The work was done on a cello (see photo). Eggers worked at the Bell Telephone Laboratory, Murray Hill from 1960-64 and became much interested in the research that Schelleng and Hutchins were doing, and often came to 112 Essex to discuss acoustics and play quartets with us. Since 1964 Eggers has been at the Max-Planck-Institute in Gottingen working in biophysical chemistry. A recent paper (1991) on mechanical impedance measurements of the cello as well as the 1959 one are included here.
    Eggers, Frieder
  - Eggers, Frieder - Miscellaneous, 1959-1987; E2960-102 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    Miscellaneous: Biog material. Technical:1) `Untersuchung von Corpus-Schwingungen am Violoncello', ACOUSTICA, 1959 with comments by Schelling. 2) `Mechanical Impedance Measurements Around the Violoncello', ACOUSTICA, 1991. It includes a preview version from Aachen 1987 and a revision submitted to CASJ - reviewed by Schumacher and Jansson at request of Sid Fox, ed. - subsequently withdrawn by Eggers and published in ACOUSTICA. Topics: Impedance measurements | Cello vibrations
  - Firth, Ian - Correspondence, 1988-1989; F5275-101 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    Correspondence regarding Firth's paper "Harps of the Baroque Period."
    Firth, Ian
  - Firth, Ian - Technical Papers, 1973-1977; F5275-102 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    Research findings on the cello and lute.
  - Firth, Ian - Technical Papers, 1977-1989; F5275-103 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    On the acoustics of the harp; Physics of the guitar; and other.
  - Fletcher, Donald Atkinson - Correspondence, 1959-1991; F6120-101 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    A first cousin of Carleen M. Hutchins who, after spending eight years studying organ and architecture at the Beaux Arts in Paris, was able to read French and type the English translation directly. He became very much interested in the new instruments of the Violin Octet and was most helpful in the early stages of their development, suggesting design concepts and ways to make them into a cohesive family of instruments. When the writings of Savart in l'Institut were finally found in the library of the Philadelphia Academy of Sciences (The pages were torn out of the copy in Widner, the volume missing at the Library of Congress and the Smithsonian) Donald offered to translate the whole series of articles concerning Savart's research on the violin. This has been most helpful over the years as many of Savart's ideas and experiments are basic to current research. He also translated the early work of Maupertuis which is based on the concept that the different length reeds of the spruce violin top reinforce the various frequencies, a discarded concept. Much of the information in the file is related to family matters.
    Correspondence: involving D A Fletcher, Mary Fletcher, REF, Flora Harvey, Betty Montleon, Dorothy Bergquist, and Carleen M. Hutchin, mostly personal. Includes Newsletters from Sweetbrook Nursing Home in Williamstown MA where Don & Mary lived.
    Fletcher, Donald Atkinson
  - Fletcher, Donald Atkinson - Miscellaneous, 1977; F6120-102 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    Miscellaneous: hand-drawn map, brief genealogical note, report (evidently written by school student, probably a neighbor of D A Fletcher) on the New Violin Family, type-written description of the funeral service for D A Fletcher, a negative and 2 obits; treatise on the Piano and the Pianist by D A Fletcher retyped by his niece, Dorothy Bergquist, which concludes with a letter to her daughter containing family history; treatise on instrumentation of Hector Berlioz. Topics: Piano & pianists | Berlioz instrumentation
  - Fletcher, Donald Atkinson - Translations, F6120-103 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    Translations by D A Fletcher: the 1724 Memoire on stringed instruments by Maupertuis [740 KB, PDF]; the 1819 Memoire (minus the Rapport) by Savart; and the 1840 l'Institut articles (the sections on stringed instruments) by Savart as transcribed by A Masson. Topics: Savart
  - Fletcher, Harvey - Correspondence, 1964-1972; F6130-101 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    Well known in acoustics as a founding member of the Acoustical Society of America and for many years Director of the Bell Telephone Laboratories at Murray Hill. His research on speech and hearing is widely know through his books and papers. In his retirement he developed a full scale acoustical testing facility at Brigham Young University and with associates, published a number of papers on the tones of musical instruments, especially the analysis and synthesis of violin, viola and cello tones, some of which are included here.
    Correspondence between Fletcher and Carleen Hutchins and Robert D Graham. Miscellaneous: Newspaper obits for Mrs Lorena Fletcher, wife.
    Fletcher, Harvey
  - Fletcher, Harvey - Technical Papers, 1935-1965; F6130-102.1 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    Topics: Analysis & synthesis of violin, viola & baritones | vibrato.
  - Fletcher, Harvey - Technical Papers, 1946-1969; F6130-102.2 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Fletcher, Neville - Correspondence, 1972-1998; F6140-101 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    Fletcher, Neville H. (Neville Horner)
  - Fletcher, Neville - Technical Papers, 1980-1991; F6140-102 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    Paper (4) Topics: Harmonic generation; organ pipes
  - Fletcher, William Harvey - Correspondence, 1931-1965; F6160-101 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    Uncle of Carleen Hutchins (mother's brother, father's brother in-law, and father of Donald A. Fletcher) who made violins for many years as a hobby (at least 200). Carleen Hutchins never saw his actual working set up for he had moved to Houston, Texas from Brooklyn before Carleen Hutchins became interested in string instruments. When Carleen Hutchins needed a viola she wrote to him asking if he would make her one. He replied that he only knew how to make violins, not violas, and suggested that she get in touch with his violin maker in NYC and try making one herself. After discussions with husband and family, Carleen Hutchins went to the violin maker, C. Meisel at 4 St Marks Place in the Bowery in NYC, bought a set of wood, a blueprint of a viola and a book ("Violin Making as it Was and Is" Ed Heron-Allen) and got started. The work took two years of carefully reading the book with occasional comments from Fletcher, the violin maker who spoke little English (Meisel had died and his wife was running the shop), and a salesman at Wurlitzer's. When it was done, the viola was rated the work of a good carpenter and was the only one that CMH planned to make!
    Correspondence: involving Grace Louise Clark, W H Fletcher, William Harvey Fletcher Jr., Louise Maley Hogan, Carleen Hutchins and Maud Alice Sauter
    Fletcher, William Harvey
  - Fletcher, William Harvey - Miscellaneous, 1941-; F6160-102 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    Miscellaneous: news clipping, an address, drawing of a violin outline, mailing label, obit and Fletcher-Maley genealogy. Topics: Carleen Hutchin' family.
  - Fox, Sidney - Violin Bridges: Mittenwald Violin I, 1984-1986; F7943-101.1 (Box 54, Folder 1)
    Actual violin bridges with accompanying experiments results.
    Fox, Sidney
  - Fox, Sidney - Violin Bridges: Mittenwald Violin II, 1984-1986; F7943-101.2 (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Fox, Sidney - Violin Bridges: Bailly Violin, 1985; F7943-102 (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Fox, Sidney - D.J. Bridge Dimensions, 1985; F7943-103 (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Fox, Sidney - Johnson Violin, 1985-1986; F7943-104 (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Fox, Sidney - Hutchins Mezzo Violin, 1985; F7943-105 (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - Fox, Sidney - Other Violins, 1985-1988; F7943-106 (Box 54, Folder 7)
  - Fox, Sidney - Hutchins Violas, 1985-1987; F7943-107 (Box 54, Folder 8)
  - Fox, Sidney - Other Violas, 1985-1990; F7943-108 (Box 54, Folder 9)
  - Frymoyer, Edward M. - Technical Paper, 1967; F9480-101 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    Frymoyer, a student working under Eugen Skudzryk at the Pennsylvania State University, department of physics when CMH first lectured there in the early 1960s. He became quite interested in the problems of vibration in violin bodies and kept in touch for many years. His thesis on "VIBRATION AND WAVE PROPAGATION IN CYLINDRICAL SHELLS" is included here.
    Technical: Vibration and wave propagation in cylindrical shells, 1967 - Tech. Memo. - Pennsylvania State University, Ordinance Research Laboratory, Office of Naval Research. Topics: Vibrations | Wave propagation | Cylindrical shells
    Frymoyer, Edward M.
  - Fryxell, Robert Edward - Correspondence, 1987-1989; F9488-101 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    A chemist, primarily involved in high temperature research for General Electric, first in Pittsfield, Mass. and then in Cincinnati, Ohio. Many of his developments were a basic part of the nuclear submarine and aircraft. Bob was an expert cellist whose first love was chamber music, and while living in Pittsfield, was cellist in many quartet and other chamber music sessions in Stockbridge at the home of Helen Rice. It was here that Fryxell met up with Saunders and those of us who were researching the acoustics of violins and violas and developing the instruments of the Violin Octet. He became a part of the original Saunders' research group (Hutchins, Fryxell, Saunders and Schelleng, some of whose early correspondance interchanges are in a large notebook in the CAS file) which eventually became the Catgut Acoustical Society (a name suggested jokingly by Schelleng). After the CAS was officially formed in 1963 and Hutchins had started a small Newsletter to keep in touch with the 25 or so members, Fryxell offered to be the Editor, a position which he fulfilled with great interest and expertise until his sudden death in 1988. He was a great reader and collected a fine library on all subjects relating to violins and violin making. He also did research on wood, especially the effects of moisture (see papers in the CASJ). Fryxell and his family often visited with the Hutchins in Montclair and New Hampshire where we discussed violin acoustics far into the night. Bob was wonderful friend and staunch supporter of the CAS.
    Correspondence: Robert Fryxell Memorial fund correspondence between Carleen Hutchins, Marjorie K. Fryxell, and various donors to the fund.
    Fryxell, Robert Edward
  - Fryxell, Robert Edward - Correspondence, 1959-1969; F9488-102 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    Correspondence: mainly involving Fryxell and Carleen Hutchins. Other correspondents include: Virginia Apgar, A.H. Benade, Yehudi Menuhin, & J.C. Schelleng. Also, articles and data on items for the Newsletter
  - Fryxell, Robert Edward - Correspondence, 1970-1986; F9488-103 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Fryxell, Robert Edward - Miscellaneous, 1963-1991; F9488-104 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Miscellaneous: Family correspondence from Marjorie and Eric Fryxell; birth announcements; Xmas cards
  - Fryxell, Robert Edward - Miscellaneous, 1983-1986; F9488-105 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    Miscellaneous: Obit. & biog. material; musical memoirs of REF; description of Elastomat equipment [2.84 MB, PDF] & sample output (graphs); news clippings on Janos Starker & Regina Fryxell (mother); notes on violin construction; bibliography on violin making, etc.; notice of CAS meeting
  - Fryxell, Robert Edward - Technical Papers, 1949-1982; F9488-106 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    Technical Papers: 12 in chemistry - 3 on instruments: weather effects, bow hair, & varnish.
  - Fulton, William M. - Correspondence with Carleen Hutchins, 1968-1993; F9747-101 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    Fulton, William M.
  - Fulton, William M. - Technical Papers, 1968-1990; F9747-102 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    Published papers on violin varnish; bent violin top
  - Ghelmeziu, Nicolae - Correspondence, 1974; G4125-101 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    Foremost researcher in wood technology in Romania. Specifically, Director in the Institute for Research and Technological Design for the Wood Industry in Bucharest. See Benchmark vol 5, CASNL #17 or B4270 - Beldie, Ion Paul, for paper `On the characteristics of resonance spruce wood'.
    Correspondence with Carleen Hutchins; Miscellaneous: Brief biography.
    Ghelmeziu, Nicolae
  - Goodkind, Herbert - Miscellaneous, 1976-1978; G6525-101 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    Correspondence with Carleen Hutchins on joining the Violin Society of America and Catgut; materials on his research on Antonio Stradivari
    Goodkind, Herbert K.
  - Graham, Thomas S. - Dissertation, 1969; G7420-101 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    A graduate student working under Eugen Skudzryk at the Pennsylvania State University department of Physics. His thesis (included here) on "Long Wavelength Acoustic Holography" (1969) shows that this method can be used as a means of studying sound radiation from vibrating objects. This method was based on long wavelengths, but it was not until a further development by Earl Williams, another of Skudzryk's students, using short wavelengths that it could be applied to the surface of a violin.
    Long Wavelength Acoustic Holography, 1969, PhD Thesis in Engineering Acoustics (Pennsylvania State University). Topics: Acoustic Holography
    Graham, Thomas S.
  - Groupe d'Acoustique Musicale - Bulletins, 1963-1965; G8825-101.1 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    A group organized by Emile Leipp for the study of and publication of papers in musical acoustics. The file contains 45 issues from the first in 1963 to issue #99 in 1978.
    Groupe d' Acoustique Musicale
  - Groupe d'Acoustique Musicale - Bulletins, 1966; G8825-101.2 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Groupe d'Acoustique Musicale - Bulletins, 1967; G8825-101.3 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Groupe d'Acoustique Musicale - Bulletins, 1968-1969; G8825-102.1 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Groupe d'Acoustique Musicale - Bulletins, 1969-1970; G8825-102.2 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Groupe d'Acoustique Musicale - Bulletins, 1971-1978; G8825-102.3 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Hacklinger, Max - Correspondence, 1977-1994; H1225-101 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    Hacklinger, Max
  - Hacklinger, Max - Technical Papers, 1978-1993; H1225-102 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    Papers (2): Violin Timbre and Bridge Frequency Response; Violin Adjustment - Strings and Bridges; Article (1): Roger Hargrave Enthuses about Max Hacklinger's Deft Thickness Measuring Gauge.